Guide to the Richard H. Clow Family Papers 1864-1939
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Richard H. Clow Family Papers
1864-1939
Montana State University-Bozeman Library, Merrill G Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2596, MtBC, us
Clow, Richard H., 1847-1926
.2 linear feet
The Richard H. Clow Family Papers consist of letters, photographs, and a biography of Richard H. Clow titled Rough Enough (2012) by Richard H. McBee. Topics include family news and some local conditions in San Jose, California, Hawaii, and Seattle, Washington.
Biographical Note
Richard H. Clow (1847-1926) was born in Nova Scotia, Canada and raised for much of his boyhood by his sister Agnes Louise Clow Cruikshank of Boston, Massachusetts. In 1864, Richard got permission to enlist in the Union army as a seventeen-year-old and was initially placed as a 100 day enlistee with the 22nd Massachusetts Volunteer Infantry. He trained at several Boston area facilities including Readville and Gallops Island. He transferred to the 56th Massachuesetts Volunteer Infantry after his first 100 days and was sent to the Army of the Potomac outside of Petersburg, Virginia. Clow took part in some of the final battles of the war in Virginia and mustered out in the summer of 1865 after participating in the Grand Review in Washington, D. C. After the war Clow enlisted in the 13th United States Infantry and served at several posts on the northern plains. After that enlistment he lived in Iowa, the Dakotas, Nebraska, Idaho and finally Oregon where he ran a hotel and prospected for gold. Clow married twice; first to Mary Bingham in 1870, and after her death to Melinda Story in 1880. The couple had two children, Cora and Robert. A grandniece of Richard H. Clow was Bertha Cochrane Clow, a professor of home economics at Montana State University, Bozeman.
The family papers of Richard H. Clow consist of letters he wrote from Massachusetts and Virginia to his sister Agnes during the Civil War, a letter he wrote from Fort Buford, North Dakota to his sister Bertha during his Indian Wars service, letters from Clow’s sister Bertha to his daughter Cora, and other correspondents from other family members. Most letters contain family news and some local conditions in San Jose, California, Hawaii, and Seattle, Washington. Sixty family photographs are also included, along with a biography of Richard H. Clow titled Rough Enough (2012) written by Richard H. McBee, Clow’s great-grandson and various genealogy notes gathered by McBee. The items in this collection have been individually calendared.
This collection is open for research.
Original letters, diary, photographs, and ephemera created or collected by Richard Harding Clow were donated to Montana State University by Richard H. McBee, Jr., Hood River, Oregon on February 24, 2015. Some of this material has been transcribed and published in McBee’s book, Rough Enough (Saratoga Village, California: American Book Classics, 2012).
Home and Family; Military; Native Americans
- Civil War Letters written by Richard H. Clow (RHC) to sister Agnes (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Readville, Massachusetts, September 8,1864
  - Gallops Island, Massachusetts, February 5,1865
    2nd Enlistment for three years
  - Gallops Island, Massachusetts, February 11,1865
  - Gallops Island, Massachusetts, February 15,1865
  - Fort Hayes, Petersburg Virginia, February [March?] 12, 1965
  - Fort Hayes, Petersburg Virginia, February 23,1865
  - Fort Hayes, Petersburg Virginia, April 1,1865
  - On the Route to and at Appomattox, Virginia, April 9,1865
  - Appomattox, Virginia, April 15,1865
  - Alexandria, Virginia, April 29,1865
  - Alexandria, Virginia, May 24,1865
  - Alexandria, Virginia, June 15, 1865
  - Alexandria, Virginia, July 2,1865
- Letters by Sarah Wyman Redman to granddaughter Alice Clow, circa 1864-1868 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Hammonton, Atlantic County New Jersey, Undated
    with envelope
  - Harbor Creek, Undated
  - Harbor Creek, March 17
  - Harbor Creek, March 19
  - Harbor Creek, May 7,1864
  - Harbor Creek, November 27
- John Stevenet Clow, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, letter to Alex Cruikshan, June 16, 1865 (Box-folder 1/3)
- RHC, Fort Buford, Dakota Territory, letter to sister Bertha R. Clow, September 28, 1869 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Letters from Bertha R. Clow to Cora Clow, 1900-1915 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - San Jose, California, October 19, 1900
  - San Jose, California, November 1900
  - San Jose, California, January 7, 1901
  - San Jose, California, January 11, 1901
  - San Jose, California, August 24, 1901
  - San Jose, California, May 17, 1916
  - San Jose, California, June 29, 1925
  - San Jose, California, October 11, 1925
- Letters from Bertha R. Clow to RHC, circa 1910 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Chicago, Illinois, August 29, [1909?]
  - Italy, April 21, 1910
    with 2 envelopes
  - San Jose, California, Undated [1910?]
- Letters from RHC and Melinda Clow to daughter Cora Clow, 1912-1915 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - RHC, Granite, Oregon, July 3, 1912
  - Melinda Clow, Mapleton, Oregon, June 20, 1915
- Lucia Shepardson, Hawaii, letter to cousin Cora Clow, March 15, 1912 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Letters from Bertha Shepardson to cousin Cora Clow, 1917-1932 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Seattle, Washington, January 17, 1917
  - Seattle, Washington, February 10, 1926
  - Seattle, Washington, August 8, 1926
  - Seattle, Washington, August 18, 1932
- Frank Richards, Beverly Hills, California, letter to RHC, August 19, 1926 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Diary of RHC, circa 1870s-1880s (Box-folder 1/11)
- Ephemera (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Marriage Certificate for RHC and Melinda Story, Deadwood, Dakota Territory, November 25, 1880
  - Redman-Wyaman coat of arms and genealogy notes
  - Lucia Shepardson, The Butterfly Trees (Monterrey: Herald Printers, 1939)
  - Business card, Eagle House, Cheyenne, Wyoming, circa 1880
- Photographs #1-10 (Box-folder 1/13)
  RHC ancestors
  - #1. Rchard Sparrow Redman
    (two copies)
  - #2. Sarah Wyman
  - #3. Sarah Wyman
  - #4. David Ferinbaugh Clow
  - #5. Ann Moore Clow
  - #6. Captain George J. Clow
  - #7. John Stevenet Clow
  - #8. Sarah Leighton Clow
  - #9. “Prairie Chickens,” carte de visite by John S. Clow
  - #10. “Old Hebrew Coin,” carte de visite by John S. Clow
- Photographs #11-20 (Box-folder 1/14)
  RHC and immediate family
  - #11. RHC, circa 1867
  - #12. Melinda Story and family, circa 1870s
  - #13. RHC and Melina, wedding photograph, 1880
  - #14. RHC, Melinda and Cora Cochraine Clow, 1886
  - #15. RHC, Melinda, Cora, and Robert Denton Clow, 1894
  - #16. RHC and Florence Shepardson, circa 1920
  - #17. RHC and Richard Harding McBee, May 15, 1920
  - #18. Melinda Story Clow, circa 1920s
  - #19. Melinda Story Clow and Richard Harding McBee
  - #20. Melinda Story Clow
- Photographs #21-30 (Box-folder 1/15)
  RHC siblings and families
  - #21. Agnes Louise Clow Cruikshank
  - #22. Agnes Louise Clow Cruikshank
  - #23. Agnes Louise Clow Cruikshank
  - #24. Alice Ana Clow Shepardson
  - #25. Alice Ana Clow Shepardson
  - #26. Alice Ana Clow Shepardson
  - #27. Alice Ana Clow Shepardson with children
  - #28. George Wyman Clow
  - #29. George Wyman Clow
  - #30. Thomas Herbert Clow
- Photographs #31-40 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - #31. Jessie B. Clow
  - #32. Jessie B. Clow
  - #33. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane
  - #34. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane
  - #35. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane, 1898
  - #36. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane, 1911
  - #37. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane, circa 1920
  - #38. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane and Hubert Kelly
  - #39. Dr. A. H. Cochrane
  - #40. Robert Denton Clow
- Photographs #41-47 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - #41. Celinda Warren Burnap Clow
  - #42. Celinda Warren Burnap Clow and Frederick Redman Clow
  - #43. Frederick Redman Clow
  - #44. John Sherwin Clow
  - #45. Celinda B. Hadden
  - #46. Richard H. McBee, Sr.
  - #47. Bertha Cochrane Clow and family at home, Oshkosh, Wisconsin
  - #48. RHC and family, interior of Hotel Mapleton, Oregon
  - #49. RHC and family, exterior of Hotel Mapleton, Oregon
  - #50. Exterior of Hotel Mapleton, Oregon
- Photographs #51-60 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - #51. Melinda Clow and Richard H. McBee, Sr., 1916
  - #52. Bertha R. Clow Cochrane home, San Jose, California
  - #53. Hand carved deer
  - #54-60. Tombstones at Larpenteur Cemetery, Little Sioux, Iowa
- Research materials collected by Richard H. McBee, Jr., including his book, Rough Enough, (2012) (Box-folder 1/19)
  RHC enlistment records from NARA, genealogy notes